<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The coppy of a letter and commission, of the King of Spaine, Phillip the third, sent vnto the vice-roy of Portugall, dated the 20. day of Iune, in the yeare of our Lord God. 1602 Wherein the dealings and trade of ships &amp; marchandize is forbidden, with the subiectes of Holland, Zealand and England, &amp;c. with the said lands and countries of Spaine and Portugall. Whereby appeareth the inueterate, and continuall malice of the said Spaniards, against the dominions of England, Holland and Zealand, &amp;c. Truely translated out of the Spanish originall, into the Dutch tongue; and now translated againe out of the Dutch copye, into English.</title>
            <author>Spain. Sovereign (1598-1621 : Philip III)</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1602</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 14 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 7 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A09561</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 19839</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S119177</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99854384</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99854384</idno>
            <idno type="VID">19802</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A09561)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 19802)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1554:06)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The coppy of a letter and commission, of the King of Spaine, Phillip the third, sent vnto the vice-roy of Portugall, dated the 20. day of Iune, in the yeare of our Lord God. 1602 Wherein the dealings and trade of ships &amp; marchandize is forbidden, with the subiectes of Holland, Zealand and England, &amp;c. with the said lands and countries of Spaine and Portugall. Whereby appeareth the inueterate, and continuall malice of the said Spaniards, against the dominions of England, Holland and Zealand, &amp;c. Truely translated out of the Spanish originall, into the Dutch tongue; and now translated againe out of the Dutch copye, into English.</title>
                  <author>Spain. Sovereign (1598-1621 : Philip III)</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 8 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed [by E. Allde] for Thomas Pauier, and are to be solde at his shop in Cornehill, at the signe of the Cat and Parets, neere the Royall Exchange,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1602.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Netherlands --  Commerce --  History --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Spain --  Commerce --  History --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-05</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Rekeyed and resubmitted</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:19802:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>The Coppy of a Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter and Commiſsion, of the King of
<hi>Spaine,</hi> Phillip the third, ſent vnto the Vice-roy of Portugall,
dated the 20. day of Iune, In the yeare of our Lord God. 1602.</p>
            <p>Wherein the dealings and trade of Ships &amp; Marchandize is
forbidden, with the ſubiectes of Holland, Zealand and England, &amp;c. with
the ſaid Lands and Countries of Spaine and Portugall.</p>
            <p>Whereby appeareth the inueterate, and continuall malice of the
ſaid Spaniards, againſt the Dominions of England, Holland and Zealand,
&amp;c.</p>
            <p>Truely tranſlated out of the Spaniſh originall, into the
Dutch tongue; and now tranſlated againe out of the Dutch Copye, into
Engliſh.</p>
            <p>LONDON, Printed for Thomas Pauier, and are to be ſolde at his
ſhop in Cornehill, at the ſigne of the Cat and Parets, neere the Royall
Exchange, 1602.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:19802:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:19802:2"/>
            <head>To the curteous Reader.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">C</seg>Vrteous Reader, after that Phillip the ſecond of that name
King of Spaine, had vexed theſe Countries of Holland and Zealand, with
tedious and continual wars, and with many Imbargos or arreſtes, made vpon
their Ships and Merchandize, to the mighty hindrance of their Nauigation and
Mariners, &amp; to the great damage and ouerthrow of many honeſt Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chants:
And not therewith contented, vſed more<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouer his great Tiranye againſt the
Maſters and Mariners, putting them into his Gallyes, and like vnto poore
miſerable ſlaues, with chaines and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tollerable trauailes and labours
tormenting them, vntill ſuch time as the Almighty God (by the wiſe dealings
of the Honorable Lords the States) at laſt did ſend releaſe and freedome
vnto a great nu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ber, which then remained aliue. And after this, his ſonne,
Phillip the third, comming to the Crowne after the death of his Father,
ſeeketh &amp; practiſeth to Imitate herein, the waies &amp; foote-ſteps
of his <pb facs="tcp:19802:3"/>Father, as it appeareth moſt
plainly by this Letter, dated the 20. day of Iune 1602. ſent vnto the
Vice-roy of Portugall: Wherein hee declareth thoſe of Holland and Zealand,
for enemyes and rebels to God and his Maieſty: Notwithſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing they were
neuer bound by oath of dutye vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to him, nor euer were his ſubiects: meaning
in this ſort to rule and gouerne ouer them as his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther hath done before
him: which is nothing at al to be wondred at, ſeeing he hath bin nouriſhed
and brought vp vnder the wings of the holie fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers of the Spaniſh
Inquiſition: wee haue in ſuch ſort foſtred him, that they name him to
be <hi>Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mani generis deſiderium,</hi> that by him they may fullie ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect
their rage and tyranie according to their owne wiſhed deſire, to the
ſurpreſſion of theſe lands and their priueledges, and alſo to the
rooting out of Gods holye word, from which our mercifull God defend and keepe
vs. Amen.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="edict">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:19802:3"/>
            <head>An Edict, ſet foorth &amp; publiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by the King of
Spaine, againſt all Ships and their lading, comming out of England, Hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,
and Zealand: tearming them by the names of Rebels of God and of his
Maieſty.</head>
            <opener>
               <signed>The King.</signed>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>Arqueſſe of <hi>Caſtel Rodrigo,</hi> principall of my
Secret Councell, my Viceroy and Captaine Generall in the Kingdome of Portugall.
You haue vnderſtood long ſince, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> cauſes which moou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the K. my Lord
(whome God hath taken vnto him) to prohibit the trade &amp; dealings, which my
rebels of Holland &amp; Zea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land vſed in theſe Countries &amp; Kingdomes,
w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the Engliſh, &amp; other enemies of our Lord God, &amp; of my kingdoms:
as alſo y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> reaſons which haue hapned in my time co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cerning y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame
matter, &amp; <pb n="2" facs="tcp:19802:4"/>ſuch as haue
lately hapned, your ſelfe beeing preſent in Councell, when the ſame was
reſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued vpon and determined. And ſeeing that at this preſent time, many
reaſons concurre, moouing vs to the execution of the ſaid prohi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bition, and
to ſee that ſuch orders as are there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in preſcribed, be ſeuerely helde
and maintain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed: my ſelfe being by diuers enformed (that not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding
the ſaid orders) the aforeſaid Engliſhmen, Rebels, and what enemies
elſe ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer, haue in no other place elſewhere ſo com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon and frequent
trade, as in the Hauens of theſe our dominions, dayly ariuing in our ſaid
Hauens, with their own Ships laden, &amp; with falſe and cullored proofes and
Paſports, as if they came from free Citties or Townes, or elſe with the
Ships of the high Dutch, or other ſtrange Ships: although that by the nature
of the ſaid lading it is preſumed that the commo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dities are of the Ilands,
or Engliſh: the keep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the ſaid ordenances (ſo made &amp;
publiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed vpon all theſe reaſons) being of ſo great importance, that
the reducing of the ſtate of the ſame countries dependeth thereon. Whereof
I haue reſolued, that this contraction and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morce ſhal be wholy broken
and prohibited, to the ende that therewith alſo the moleſtations (which
vnder colour heerof) haue been accuſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med to be vſed towards the ſhips
of my friends and confederates, may ceaſe, which haue been
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:19802:4"/>eſteemed for enemies, and
that the one ceaſing, the other ſhall be prohibited. To which ende I haue
conſented, that you onely, &amp; ſuch perſons (as your ſelfe ſhall
nominate) haue power and authoritie to take knowledge of all matters and
occurrences appertaining to theſe arreſtes. Likewiſe I giue vnto you
power and authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie by vertue of this preſent commiſſion and fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cultie,
to viſit, and to giue order that all Ships of ſtrangers which ſhall come
into the Hauens of theſe our ſaid kingdomes may bee viſited, naming and
appointing thereunto in euerye Hauen, ſome one perſon of ſuch qualitie
&amp; cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit, that your ſelfe may bee therein quiet and contented, which
ſhall vſe therein ſuch faithful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes and integritie, as may be needefull
and ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary, or at leaſt wiſe in the moſt frequented Hauens of
moſte importaunce, with com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion that to this effect they may ſeaze
on all, or at leaſt wiſe on ſuch as ſhal fall firſt into their hands:
&amp; ſuch as ſhall be found to be of the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bels, Engliſh, or other myne
enemies, you ſhall arreſt all the perſons which ſhall come in the
ſame Shippes: and ſhall alſo attache and lay handes on all the goods and
Marchandize which they ſhall bring, to the ende that (the ſame being
conuinced, and prooued to come fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the landes of enemies and Rebels, and the
ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions being proſecuted according to forme of <pb n="4" facs="tcp:19802:5"/>law)
you condemne the ſame to be loſt and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fiſcated, as by me is ordained,
applycating the ſame according to the accuſtomed manner, as more
perticularly at large appeareth in the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foreſaid ordinances, and others
which I eſteeme as inſerted heereunto. And whatſoeuer you ſhall in this
manner condemne and confiſcate, you ſhall preſently cauſe to be
ſolde, without let or hindrance of any appeale whatſoeuer, which may in the
<hi>Interim</hi> happen, and the ſame ſhall be done by Port ſale or
Out-cry, to the moſt benefit and profit you can. Vnto all which do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, the
ſercher Generall <hi>Don Iuan de Londo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na,</hi> ſhall repayre to be
preſent, as ſoone as any ſuch Shippes or any of them ſhall be taken or
ſeazed: and that the ſame Shippes, and the goods therein laden, ſhall be
Inuentared, if the ſame doe happen where hee ſhall be reſident. And for
other places thereabouts, ſuch other as ſhall be appointed for this
ſeruice in his name. And all ſuch ſummes of money as ſhall pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceede
heereof, you ſhall giue order that the ſame ſhall be put into a Chriſt,
with three keyes, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing different lockes, in the preſence of the
be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forenamed ſercher Generall: whereof you ſhal haue one, <hi>Don Iuan de
Londona</hi> (aforeſaid) the ſecond, and the third ſhall be deliuered
vnto the Paymaſter, who ſhall receiue theſe moneyes. And my will and
pleaſure is, that no man ſhal <pb n="5" facs="tcp:19802:5"/>touch
the ſame money, for any cauſe whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer, that ſhall happen for my
ſeruice, how ſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all or importunate the ſame may bee, without my
perticular order before had. And in the Hauens betweene <hi>Duero</hi> and
<hi>Mino</hi> where the like diligence is needfull, the ſame ſhall bee
ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compliſhed in the preſence of ſuch as ſhall ſerue there for
ſercher of the Martiall men in thoſe quarters: who alſo ſhall haue one
key of the Chiſt which ſhall there be appointed, and the ſecond ſhall
be giuen to him whome you ſhall thereunto nominate, and the third ſhall
ſerue for the Paymaſter generall, vſing ſuch dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence as is before
ſpecifyed. And to the ende that men may heerein proceed with ſuch
iuſtifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation and vpright dealing, as is thereunto ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary or
needfull: you are heereby aduertiſed, that all the appeales (which for
Iuſtice ſake may in theſe cauſes take place, made from the ſentences
pronounced by you, or by ſuch perſons as by your commiſſion ſhall be
thereunto ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed) ſhall bee made before my Councell at warres, and not
before any others ſitting in place of Iuſtice, or other Courts
whatſoeuer. To all which, and to euery part therof, &amp; what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer
elſe ſhall thereto appertaine, depend ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, or concerne the ſame: I
giue and lend you ſo full power, commiſſion &amp; authority: &amp; to
ſuch perſons as you ſhal thereunto appoint or nomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate, as therunto
ſhall be needfull and requiſite. <pb n="6" facs="tcp:19802:6"/>And
I commaund that no man, of what quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, reſpect, or condition ſoeuer,
ſhal heerein inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meddle or intrude himſelfe, but you onely, and ſuch
perſons as you ſhall thereunto nominate, and that ſuch perſons ſhall
remit and ſend vnto you, &amp; to ſuch perſons which ſhal execute this
commiſſion by your appointment, all ſuch pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſes and actions,
which are or ſhall be brought into their Courts, touching queſtions and
diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rences vpon goods, comming out of Holland, Zealand, and England: and
alſo I command that they ſeaze, forbeare, and forbid all farther
proceedings therin, eyther dyrectly or vndirect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and al ſuch notaries or
other perſons, which ſhall haue any manner of ſuch inuentaries, or
actions, concerning and belonging vnto any ſuch arreſtes or
poſſeſſions, I commaund them to deliuer vnto you the originals, as
ſoone as you ſhall demaund the ſame, on ſuch penalty as you ſhall
ſet thereon. Alſo, I commaund the Maſter of the Requeſtes, and the
Gouernour of the Hauens, and the <hi>Corregidores,</hi> and all other Iudges,
and Courts of my Kingdome of <hi>Por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tugall,</hi> that they hinder you not in
the execution of theſe matters before written: but that they ſhew vnto you
all needfull fauour, helpe and aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtance: and to al others (as is
aforeſaid) which you ſhall nominate or appoint: and that they ſhall
inuiolably follow and keepe, ſuch orders which you ſhall eyther giue, or
ſend them, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe <pb n="7" facs="tcp:19802:6"/>the
neceſſity of our ſeruice ſo requireth.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>Giuen at S. <hi>Lorenco</hi>
                  <date>the <hi>20.</hi> day of Iune
<hi>1602.</hi>
                  </date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>Vnder written, <hi>L.</hi> the King, by the
commaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement of our King. <hi>Eſteuan de Ibarra.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <head>Don <hi>Iohn Chriſtoual de Moura Marques</hi> of the
<hi>Caſtel Rodrigo,</hi> great Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mander of <hi>Altcateo,</hi> one of the
Priuie Councell of his Maieſtie. <hi>Vice-roy</hi> and Captaine Generall in
this Kingdome of <hi>Portugall.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">D</seg>Octer <hi>Michiel de la Plaha,</hi> the Ship S.
<hi>Iacob,</hi> and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers are in this Hauen ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſted and attached,
be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it is reported that they are of, or come from the Enemies Countries:
and for aſmuch as it is needefull that their cauſes bee determined withall
ſuch dilligence and forme as his Maieſty hath writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten vnto me in his
Kinglie letter the xx. of Iune this preſent yeare, wherof the Attenticke
cop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pie ſhall bee deliuered vnto you, heerewith I doe binde and nominate you,
to the ende that you follow the contents thereof in ſuch manner as if the
ſame were directed vnto you, to deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine the cauſe of the ſaid Ships,
withal the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cidents, <pb n="8" facs="tcp:19802:7"/>and
dependants thereof, and to nomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate, <hi>Notaries, Alguaſyl,</hi> &amp;
other ſeruants and Officers which therunto are needefull: and to cauſe
ſuch ſalarye to be giuen vnto them as you ſhall appoint. To all which I
giue you all, and the ſame power &amp; authority as I my ſelfe haue from
his Maieſtie: And for as much as in the meane ſeaſon, I haue not any
thing to the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trarye to commaund you: you ſhall admit and imbrace all
ſuch denuntiations, and informati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons as ſhall be brought vnto you,
concerning this matter: And ſhall determine the ſame ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the
contents of the ſaid letter.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>Acted at <hi>Liſborne</hi>
                  <date>the <hi>10.</hi> day of Auguſt.
<hi>1602.</hi>
                  </date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Don Chriſtouall.</hi> At the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundement of his
Excelency.<hi>Iohn Baſques de Camara.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
            <trailer>FJNIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:19802:7"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
